We've already talked about access and modifiers in TypeScript classes and in this lesson
we're going to expand upon our knowledge even further.
So TypeScript has a way of controlling which parts of a class are visible and accessible.
We're going to already learn about public and provide it, but also going to learn about
protected, which is used to enforce encapsulation and protect internal state and only expose
what's necessary.
So in terms of a class that are three access modifiers, public, private and protected.
So the public, as an example shows here, allows us, which is the deep.
So the public, which this code shows here, is the default and that allows us to access
the code from anywhere we like.
So we just set up a public property here and we can just also a public.
So we've set up a public property here as well as a public method and that means we can
just access the property in the way anywhere we want here.
So now let's paste an example.
So we have a bank account.
Now this is obviously we don't want anyone's access to balance directly.
We have to use some approved methods.
So we've now specified private on this property here and we have these two individual
methods.
And again, don't forget that if it's not actually specifically mentioned, it's public,
then these by default are going to be made public.
So we can now create an instance of that particular class, let's say const account equals
new bank account.
And if we try to access the balance directly, we can't specify it.
We have to, of course, use the two approved members.
So private members are only accessible inside the class itself, which is a great for protecting
internal state.
So now we've talked about public and we talked about private.
So this just leaves us with the other access modifier, which is protected.
So protected allows our members inside our class to be accessible within the class and
also any class that inherits from it, but not outside if it doesn't inherit from it.
So I'm just going to do a little example, let's have a class of animal, we're going
to have a protected property called sound, which is going to be a string and just said it to a generic
sound on this particular animal.
That's have a public method called make a sound, going to return a string and just simply
do this sound.
And now we're going to create the second class and the second class is going to extend
the animal class.
And we're going to define a method called bark, which is a public method, which returns
a string, let's say return dog says dollar this dot sound.
So this sound of course is inheriting from our animal class.
Now this is absolutely fine because we can access this because the dog is inheriting from
our animal class, but if we try to create an instance of the animal class itself, let's
do var my animal equals new animal, and now we're going to try and access that property
sound we can't because we are doing it, we're not actually inheriting that I have formed
the animal directly.
This access modifiers allow us us to control visibility and protect our class logics.